<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on Vishal Chovatiya</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on Vishal Chovatiya</description>
    <image>
      <title>Vishal Chovatiya</title>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.128.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Watchdog Timer(WDT) &amp; Window Watchdog Timer(WWDT)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/watchdog-timer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/watchdog-timer/</guid>
      <description>In the embedded systems/SoCs, Watchdog Timer(WDT) is the basic, subtle and essential circuit/ic. No matter, how good you write your firmware/software. There are always unexpected situations like your program may stick in an infinite loop, hung somewhere or hardware burn-out/failure. To combat these unexpected situations, we need some circuitry that keeps monitoring the main system/application and in case of unexpected events, it restarts the system. Even the windows-like operating system use the watchdog timer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Install and Configure VNC Server on Linux!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-to-install-configure-vncserver-linux-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-to-install-configure-vncserver-linux-2/</guid>
      <description>In the early days of my career, I used to work on Linux machines remotely. In those days, I was not knowing about SSH &amp;amp; all and people around me was using Putty as it was very easy &amp;amp; simple. Open source as well. You just have to enter IP &amp;amp; Port and you would get command-line access to remote machine. here, we will discuss &amp;ldquo;how to install and configure VNC server on Linux?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Does Virtual Memory Work?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-does-virtual-memory-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-does-virtual-memory-work/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever wondered , How game of size 8 GB is running on a computer has 4 GB of RAM only? or You can play multiple movies simultaneously combined size more than RAM size? If you are a software developer, you may come across a word like multi-tasking or multiprocessing which is key concept behind this. In other words, it creates virtual memory which is a memory management technique. Here we will see how it works</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
